Susanth Guru

Data Engineer Kumbakonam, Tamilnadu, India

L+91 9500980912 ■ susanth.guru.29@gmail.com Inlinkedin.com/in/susanthguru Q github.com/susanth-g

About

Having **6 years** of experience in documenting, designing and implementing solutions for problems of multiple usecases by analysing technologies that fit. I also have hands on experience with multiple technologies like **Hadoop**, **HIVE**, **Hbase**, **Spark**, **Cloudera**, **GCP** and **Kafka** to complete data ingestion pipe lines and provision of ingested data to the product user interface.

Work Experience

Paypal ☑ Feb 2022 - Present

Data Engineer Chennai, Tamil Nadu

- Designed and implemented solutions based on Spark Streaming with Pubsub and Bigquery for creating data ingestion pipelines.
- Developed Bash scripts, SQL scripts, pySpark and Python scripts to move or recover data from multiple sources such as log files,
 JSON files and HIVE parquet files.

CanGo Networks Pvt Ltd <a>C

Nov 2019 - Feb 2022

Chennai, Tamil Nadu

Lead Big Data Developer

- Designed and implemented solutions based on core JAVA for CoreServices and SpringBoot for APIs.
- Developed spark based and multithreaded performant oriented applications based on JAVA to collect and parse data from various data sources such as FTP, Command output from SSH Session, messaging queues like Kafka and Pubsub.

National Payments Corporation of India 2

Jul 2017 - Nov 2019

Associate Enterprise Architect

- Chennai, Tamil Nadu
- Designed and implemented solutions based on HIVE and HBASE, Apache NIFI and Apache Phoenix.
- **Developed utility jars** to help operations team for scheduled daily reports which reduced the effort and time to generate reports manually everyday.

Technical Skills

Languages and Scripts: Java 8, Spring Boot, SQL, Arango QL, Shell Script, Docker YAML (basic), Python (Only to script)

DataBase Technologies (SQL): MySQL, Postgres, HIVE, Impala

DataBase Technologies (NoSQL): HBase, ArangoDB, Elastic Search

Cloud Technologies: GCP [BigQuery, PubSub, CloudStorage, CloudSQL, DataProc, Kubernetes], AWS [S3 Bucket]

Big Data Technologies: Hadoop, Apache Spark, Apache NIFI, Spark SQL, Cloudera

Developer Tools: VS Code, Eclipse, SublimeText 4, NP++, StarUML, draw.io

Terminal Tools: bash, tmux, less, vim, htop, top

Other Technologies/Framework: Linux, Git, SVN, JUnit, Microservices, Rserve, REST API, Kubernetes, Docker, RASA ChatBot

Projects

Cloud Migration | Spark Streaming, Pubsub, Bigquery, Dataproc, SQL, JAVA, Python, HIVE

Role: Data Engineer

- Developed a **JAVA based spark streaming** JAR with editable config file to fetch data from Pubsub then transform, validate and push into BQ tables.
- **Recovered lost data in HIVE** by regenerating data from raw log files by developing a **python** script, then read and pushed the data to HIVE using **Spark** and HQL.

NIMS - Network Inventory Management System | Core JAVA, JAVA Future, Jsch Library, ArangoDB

Role: Lead and Developer

- · Led a small team of UI and API developers.
- Designed and Implemented the complete **Data collection service** using **core JAVA** to fetch and parse data from more than **24000 devices using SSH protocol** for different vendors on daily basis.

MAXIS - OptiGo Al Product | JAVA Spark, Hive, Impala, MySQL, SpringBoot

Role: Developer

- Implemented a **Data parser** to populate performance data from csv or xml files using **Spark SQL** into Hive database by applying pivots and transformations over dataframes as required. Optimised Spark SQL performance with persistence.
- Designed and implemented a KQI calculator using spark SQL to re-aggregate performance data based on configurations to
 calculate KQI and push to Hive tables in a scheduled time interval.
- Developed CRUD API using SpringBoot to configure KQI from UI.
- Worked closely with Datascience team to invoke R code from JAVA Spring Boot with RServe.

Transaction Enquiry System - NPCI UPI, NACH | Java HTTP Servlet, Apache NIFI, Hbase, Sqoop

Role: Developer

- Designed and implemented a data ingestion pipeline using **sqoop** to fetch daily data from postgres and populate into Hive. Then using **Apache NIFI** to fetch transaction data and form rowkey based on the data, then push to Hbase.
- Implemented APIs using JAVA HTTP Servlet to fetch data from Hbase using Apache Phoenix JDBC connection.

• Developed a scheduled report generation JAR to generate reports which reduced the time to generate manual reports but enabled operations to verify or analyse the data. **Publication** Emulation of IoT Gateway ☑ Jan 2017

ICCCSP - Research Gate

Education

within lab environments.

SSN, Anna university Affil. 🗗 Jun 2015 - Jun 2017 Master of Engineering (M.E.,) in Computer Science Chennai, Tamil Nadu JJCET, Anna university Affil. 🗹 Jun 2011 - May 2015 Trichy, Tamil Nadu

Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.,) in Computer Science

Emulation of IoT gateway for connecting sensor nodes in heterogenous networks

Languages

Tamil - Native, English - Fluent